GRAEME MACGILCHRIST

University College, Oxford, OX1 4BH graeme.macgilchrist@univ.ox.ac.uk (+44) 7908568289

Research interests

I have broad research interests within high-latitude physical oceanography and the interaction between the ocean circulation and other components of the climate system. My PhD work has focussed on ocean ventilation, particularly on the mechanisms and variability of deep ocean ventilation in the North Atlantic, the impact of mesoscale variability on ventilation pathways, and the role of ventilation in the uptake of carbon in the Southern Ocean.

Education

DPhil Physical Oceanography University of Oxford, U.K. Thesis: Lagrangian perspectives on ocean ventilation Supervisors: Prof. David Marshall and Dr. Helen Johnson MSc Oceanography (with Distinction) University of Southampton, U.K. Dissertation: Quantifying carbon sequestration in the Arctic Ocean (84%) Supervisor: Prof. Alberto Naveira Garabato MMath Mathematics (Hons, 1st Class) Newcastle University, U.K. Broad degree incorporating applied maths, pure maths and statistics Dissertation: Magnetic fields in accretion discs (78%)

Publications

- MacGilchrist, G.A. et al. (in prep) Characteristics and variability of deep North Atlantic ocean ventilation in an eddy-permitting numerical ocean circulation model, to be submitted to *Journal of Climate*.
- MacGilchrist, G.A. et al. (in prep) Reframing the polar Southern Ocean carbon cycle, to be submitted to *Nature Geoscience*.
- van Sebille, E. et al. (2018) Lagrangian ocean analysis: Fundamentals and practices, *Ocean Modelling*, 121: 49-75.
- Naveira Garabato, A.C., MacGilchrist, G.A et al. (2017) High latitude ocean ventilation and its role in Earth's climate transitions, *Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A*, 375: 20160324.
- MacGilchrist, G.A. et al. (2017) Characterizing the chaotic nature of ocean ventilation. *Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans*, 122: 7577-7594.
- MacGilchrist, G.A. et al. (2014) Effect of enhanced pCO2 levels on the production of DOC and TEP in short term bioassay experiments. *Biogeosciences*, 11: 3695-3706.

MacGilchrist, G.A. et al. (2014) The Arctic Ocean carbon sink. Deep Sea Research I, 86: 39-55.

Awards and Scholarships

Doctoral studies	Natural Environment Research Council PhD studentship
	CASE studentship, NERC (linked to U.K. Met Office)
	Oxford-Radcliffe-Graduate Scholar, University College
	Sykes scholarship for travel in mainland China
Masters studies	School fees bursary, University of Southampton

Educational Support Fund, Society for Underwater Technology John Raymont Fund for highest aggregate mark in MSc Oceanography
Excellence in 1 st three years, Newcastle University Individual awards for merit in 1 st and 2 nd years, Newcastle University

Workshops and summer schools

Undergraduate studies

Advanced Climate Dynamics Course Newfoundland, Canada Topic: Role of high latitudes in centennial to millennial scale climate variability.	2016	
Future of Lagrangian Ocean Modelling Workshop Imperial College, London, U.K. Invitational international workshop, organised by Erik van Sebille.	2015	
Alpine Summer School Val d'Aosta, Italy Topic: Dynamics, stochastics and predictability of the climate system.	2014	
Fluid Dynamics and Sustainability of the Environment Cambridge, U.K. Broad topics in fluid dynamics, with focus on GFD. Computational and laboratory-based practical components.	2014	
Relevant employment		
Research assistant OSMOSIS project cruise JR090, RRS James Cook Responsibilities: Operation of tethered microstructure profiler.		

Researcher University of Southampton, U.K.

2012 - 2013

Responsibilities: Publication of MSc research, further work on ocean acidification.

CTD sample collection and salinometer measurements.

Field Research Coordinator Madagascar Cultures and Nature, Ifotaka, Madagascar

2011

Responsibilities: Lead researcher in survey of invasive plant species near Ifotaka.

Coordination of U.K. students, as part of Operation Wallacea.

Teaching experience

Tutor and demonstrator University of Oxford, U.K.

2013 - 2017

Subjects: Vector Calculus, 3rd year undergraduate

Mathematics for Materials and Earth Science, 1st year undergraduate

Planet Earth, 1st year undergraduate

Physical Oceanography, 3rd year undergraduate

Responsibilities: Combination of small-group (2-5 students) tutorials and large-group

(20+ students) problem classes and demonstrations. Design and planning of weekly, hour-long tutorials.

Science outreach 2011-present

Regular lectures and events to a wide range of audiences, University of Oxford.
Fluid dynamics demonstrations to students and general public, University of Oxford.
Society for Underwater Technology Christmas Lecture at the National Maritime
Museum, Greenwich, 2013.

Tutoring with 'Science Plus Oxford', an initiative to introduce high school children to science and scientists.

Academic tutor and sports coach Future Hope, Kolkata, India

2006 & 2008

Voluntary work with disadvantaged children and young adults.

Responsibilities: Daily tutoring and sports coaching with groups of between 10 and

30 children, aged between 4 and 20.

Extra-curricular and skills

Rugby	International honours	Scotland Under 18, 19 and 20, 2005-2007 Under 19 World Cup in Dubai, 2006	
	Tynedale R.F.C.	Promotion to English National League 1, 2008 Northumberland County Cup Winner, 2008 – 2010	
	Oxford University R.F.C.	Player in Varsity Match versus Cambridge, 2013-2016 Two full Blues.	
I.T. Literacy	Proficient in MATLAB, Linux, Python, Fortran, R, TeX, and Microsoft Word.		
Research tools	Coding and analysing numerical simulations of a range of complexities. Applying dynamical systems theory to oceanographic problems. Lagrangian analysis of numerical simulations and observations. Budget calculations from box inversions.		
Languages	Native English speaker. Good spoken French.		
Music	Guitar, trumpet, piano, mandolin, ukulele.		

References

Prof. David Marshall, PhD supervisor, University of Oxford (david.marshall@physics.ox.ac.uk)
Prof. Alberto Naveira Garabato, MSc supervisor, University of Southampton (acng@noc.soton.ac.uk)
Dr. Helen Johnson, PhD supervisor, University of Oxford (helen.johnson@earth.ox.ac.uk)
Prof. Ric Williams, PhD examiner, University of Liverpool (ric@liverpool.ac.uk)